Guide to the Richard E. Gross Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Richard E. Gross papers
1963-1977
SC1023
Gross, Richard E.
1.5 Linear feet
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Materials were the gift of Teacher’s College, Columbia University.
Information about Access
Access: Materials are open to research use.
Biographical/Historical note
Gross earned his AB and MA at the University of Wisconsin and his doctorate in education at Stanford in 1951. He joined the Stanford faculty in the School of Education in 1955 and taught until his retirement in 1990.
Scope and Contents note
These papers were generated from his efforts to compile materials on all major social studies education research projects to be used by his graduate students; included are correspondence, reports, publications, and curriculum materials. Subjects of the projects include anthropology, sociology, history, geography, conservation, peace studies, racial and cultural diversity, foreign relations, law, and economics.
Access Terms
Stanford University. Graduate School of Education. -- General subdivision--Faculty.;; Social sciences--Study and teaching.
Collection Contents
- Bailey, W. & M. Rice. Development of Sequential curriculum in Anthropology for Grades 1-7, reports, outlines, and brochures, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Becker, J. M. Foreign Relations Project (Secondary), correspondence, newsletters, and publications, 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
- Biological Sciences Curriculum Study, class materials, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Civil Rights: A Case Study of Negro Leadership in Civil Rights, instructional guide, circa 1965 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Collier, M. C. Anthropology Curriculum Study Project (Secondary), newsletters, publications, and other materials, 1964-1971 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
- Diablo Valley Education Project report [peach education/conflict resolution], circa 1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Edgar, Robert W. the Impact on Learning and Retention of Specially Developed History Materials for Culturally Deprived Children: an Exploratory Study, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- ESR [Education Systems Research] Data Banks, printed materials (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Frankel, M. L. Economic Education Activities (1-12), newsletter and program description, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Gibson, J. S. The Development of Instructional Materials Pertaining to Racial and Cultural Diversity in America reports, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Gill, C. and W. Conroy. Development of Guidelines and Resource Materials on Latin America for Use in Grades I-XII, correspondence and statement, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Gross, N. Development of Sociological Materials for Use in Secondary School Instruction report (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Harnack, R. S. The Use of Electronic Computers to Improve Individualization of Instruction, correspondence and summaries, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Hawkes, G. W. A Philosophical and Historical Rationale for a New Approach to “Problems of Democracy,” correspondence and papers, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Helburn, N. High School Geography Project, correspondence, newsletters, publications, and other materials, 1964-1971 (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
- Helburn, N. High School Geography Project, Demonstration Kit (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Hennebry, H. M. Conservation Education Improvement Project, correspondence and brochure, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Joyce, B. R. Use of a Data Storage and Retrieval System to Teach Elementary School Children, correspondence, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Kastner, H. Knowledge of Economics of 11th Grade U. S. History Students, correspondence and report, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Kremple, F. A. Multimedia Visual Aids as Instructional Techniques in College History Survey Courses, correspondence and report, 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Law in American Society, printed materials, 1970-1976 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Lippitt, R. Institute for Social Research, printed materials (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Man: a Course of Study, workshop materials, 1968 and undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Man: a Course of Study, correspondence, brochures, publications, etc., 1970-1975 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Man: a Course of Study, clippings, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Problem solving in school children: two papers by Richard S. Crutchfield and Martin V. Covington, 1963-1965 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Robinson, Sheryl, “A Collection of Bibliographies: Law Education 1967-1977,” class paper (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Social Studies Projects, Centers and Related Studies, assorted lists, 1966-1973 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Tri-University Project in Elementary Education, publications, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 11)